

PhD Candidate | Sessional Lecturer | Research Software Engineer

School of Mathematics and Physics, The University of Queensland

Complex data analyses are used in every industry and scientific field, but so often with results that are hard to interpret and unintuitive. I aim to increase the transparency of complex models - making them understandable and explainable - through research at the forefront of explainable AI, as well as through teaching and communication in general. I enjoy writing code (including software packages and libraries) in R, Python, Julia and SQL. I enjoy theoretical work, and I always want to apply theoretical methods to overcome real world challenges. Aside from research, I practice relational database design, data integration, software engineering, and I teach various courses in both statistics and computer science. I currently serve as a council member and Communications Officer at the Statistical Society of Australia.

Education _

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

PhD | Statistics and Mathematics

2019-Current

• Explaining, exploring and clustering with non-linear and complex data

La Trobe University

Melbourne, VIC, AU

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE | MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS WITH FIRST CLASS HONOURS (WEIGHTED AVERAGE MARK: 97)

2014-2018

• Random fields: Long memory, and R for cosmology

Experience _____

Monash University

Melbourne, Victoria, AU

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2020-Current

• Politics & International Relations

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

CASUAL INSTRUCTOR | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2020-Current

• Master's of Data Science project support

University of Auckland Auckland Region, NZ

2018-Current

Course Instructor | New Zealand Social Statistics Network
Introduction to SQL for academics and professionals

La Trobe University

Melbourne, VIC, AU

SESSIONAL LECTURER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS

2018–Current

• Master's level meta-analysis | Master's level database fundamentals

The University of Queensland

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU 2019–2019

• Digital phenotyping for transdiagnostic clustering and psychiatric prognosis

La Trobe University

Melbourne, VIC, AU

RESEARCH SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2018-2019

· Spherical data analysis in R on the HEALPix grid

Service

COUNCIL MEMBER | COMMUNICATIONS OFFICER

2020-Current

Melbourne, VIC, AU

Dimension Reduction and Meta Analysis Research Group

Melbourne, VIC, AU 2017-Current

MEMBER | WEBSITE MAINTAINER

Statistical Society of Australia

Melbourne, Victoria, AU

Australian & New Zealand Journal of Statistics

2020-2020

Peer Reviewer (1 ARTICLE)

Campus Consultancy

Melbourne, VIC, AU

SENIOR MENTOR AND FOUNDING MEMBER

2017-2019

Describ Sahaal on Statistics and Data Saisman	Malla a coma a NIC ALL
Research School on Statistics and Data Science PEER REVIEWER (3 ARTICLES)	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2019–2019
Journal of Open Source Software	Melbourne, VIC, AU
Peer Reviewer (1 article)	2019–2019
Victorian State Emergency Services	Melbourne, VIC, AU
EMERGENCY FIRST RESPONDER	2017–2018
La Trobe University Mathematics and Statistics Society	Melbourne, VIC, AU
VICE PRESIDENT Newsletter Editor	2016–2016
In2Science	Melbourne, VIC, AU
MENTOR MATHEMATICS SCHOOL OUTREACH	2015–2015
Awards	
Vice Chancellor's Sessional Teaching Award	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, NA	2020
Three Minute Thesis People's Choice	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS	2020
Pitching Research Competition Best Written and Oral Pitch University-Wide	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, BUSINESS SCHOOL	2019
Pro Vice Chancellor's Commendation (awarded four times)	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, University-Wide	2018
Department Prize in Fourth Year Statistics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2018
David Myer's Medallion La Trobe's most prestigious undergraduate award	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, College of Science, Health and Engineering	2018
Silver Scholarship Community Involvement and Dedication to Mathematics	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University Student Union, University-Wide	2017
Department Prize in Third Year Statistics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2016
Prof CJ Eliezer Prize in Second Year Mathematics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2015
Prof Jim Morrison Prize in Chemistry Best Performing Student (awarded twice)	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, School of Molecular Sciences	2014
La Trobe Award in Community Engagement Volunteer Efforts La Trobe University, University-Wide	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2014
LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, UNIVERSITY-WIDE	2014
Publications	
Pipeline	
D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen	arXiv
EXPLAINING THE DATA OR EXPLAINING A MODEL? SHAPLEY VALUES THAT UNCOVER NON-LINEAR DEPENDENCIES	2020
M Terrett, D Fryer, T Doody, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	arXiv
SARGDV: EFFICIENT IDENTIFICATION OF GROUNDWATER-DEPENDENT VEGETATION USING SYNTHETIC APERTURE RADAR	2020
HD Nguyen, D Fryer	arXiv
A BINARY-RESPONSE REGRESSION MODEL BASED ON SUPPORT VECTOR MACHINES	2020
Published	

D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko The R Journal 2020

RCOSMO: R PACKAGE FOR ANALYSIS OF SPHERICAL, HEALPIX AND COSMOLOGICAL DATA

Astrophysics Source Code Library, D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko

2020 RCOSMO: COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS

Frontiers in Applied Mathematics D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen

and Statistics

SHAPLEY VALUE CONFIDENCE INTERVALS FOR ATTRIBUTING VARIANCE EXPLAINED

2020

ascl:

D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi

k-means on Positive Definite Matrices, and an Application to Clustering in Radar Image Sequences 2020

Research School on Statistics and D Fryer, A Olenko

Data Science

SPHERICAL DATA HANDLING AND ANALYSIS WITH R PACKAGE RCOSMO

D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Orban Journal of Open Source Software

STUDENTLIFE: TIDY HANDLING AND NAVIGATION OF A VALUABLE MOBILE-HEALTH DATASET

Presentations and events

IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence

Brisbane

2020

K-MEANS ON POSITIVE DEFINITE MATRICES, AND AN APPLICATION TO CLUSTERING IN RADAR IMAGE SEQUENCES

• Talk and conference publication

Melbourne

Statistical Society of Australia EARLY CAREER INDUSTRY SHOWCASE, CHIEF EVENT ORGANISER 2020

• 6 panelists, 180 attendees https://vimeo.com/ssavic/20200922-showcase

Victorian Research Students Meeting in Probability and Statistics

Melhourne

EXPLAINING, EXPLORING AND CLUSTERING WITH NON-LINEAR AND COMPLEX DATA

St Lucia

UO Research Video Pitch

· Building the Melbourne research student community

2020

FORECASTING PSYCHIATRIC SYMPTOMS WITH DIGITAL PHENOTYPING · First prize. youtu.be/h-m8QwLq29Y

St Lucia

UQ Three Minute Thesis Presentation

MACHINE LEARNING: THE BIG BLACK BOX

• People's choice award. vimeo.com/434959101

Melbourne

SPHERICAL DATA HANDLING AND ANALYSIS WITH R PACKAGE RCOSMO

2019

· Poster and Springer book chapter

UseR!2018 Conference

RSSDS2019 Poster Presentation

Brisbane

COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS WITH R

2018

• R package published on CRAN. https://youtu.be/7KBsguOlEHs

Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute Summer Research School

Melbourne

FUNCTIONALS OF LONG-RANGE DEPENDENT FIELDS AND HERMITE DISTRIBUTIONS Summer Research Scholarship recipient. vrs.amsi.org.au/daniel-vidali-fryer-2017/

2017

UNSW Statistical Challenges in Astronomy

Sydney

LIGHTING TALK: A NEW R PACKAGE FOR COSMOLOGY Fostering new collaborations in statistics and astronomy 2017

DANIEL FRYER · CURRICULUM VITAE